Ralph J. Pancallo Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Ralph J. Pancallo Papers.
undated, 1882-1984.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Pancallo, Ralph J.
7.25 linear feet.
Mr. Pancallo was a long-standing member of the International Typographical Union (now the Communications Workers of America). He joined ITU in 1935 when he started working as an Apprentice Printer for the Meridian Morning Record. In 1940, he started work with the New Britain Herald as a Composite Printer. In 1958, he took the position of Representative of the I.T.U., a position he held until his retirement in 1979. Ralph Pancallo also served as vice president of the Connecticut State Labor Council, secretary and president of the New Britain Central Labor Council, and as both president and treasurer of the New Britain Typographical Union #679 (now the Connecticut Typographical Union #679).
MSS19940077
Biography
Ralph J. Pancallo, son of Dominic and Mary, was born in St. John, Italy on 1 December 1912. He moved to the United States with his parents as a child. He attended public schools in Meriden, Connecticut. As an adult, he took courses at the International Typographical Union Training Center and the University of Connecticut. Ralph Pancallo married Hattie Astranowicz; they had four daughters.
Mr. Pancallo was a long-standing member of the International Typographical Union (now the Communications Workers of America). He joined ITU in 1935 when he started working as an Apprentice Printer for the Meride Morning Record. In 1940, he started work with the New Britain Herald as a Composite Printer. In 1958, he took the position of Representative of the I.T.U., a position he held until his retirement in 1979.
Ralph Pancallo also served as vice president of the Connecticut State Labor Council, secretary and president of the New Britain Central Labor Council, and as both president and treasurer of the New Britain Typographical Union #679 (now the Connecticut Typographical Union #679).
His contributions to the labor movement have been recognized with awards from various organizations including the New England Conference, the New Haven Typographical Union #47, and the (Boston) Mailers Union #1.
Scope and Content
The materials collected by Pancallo include union meeting minutes, financial ledgers, printed materials, correspondence, clippings, and convention reports, programs and films. Other materials include publications from a variety of local typographical unions as well as the AFL-CIO. The periodicals Typographical Journal (1954-1986) and Typographical Review (1958-1983, 1986) have been removed from the collection and catalogued.
Arrangement
The Ralph J. Pancallo Papers are arranged in seven series:
Series I: Subject Files ( undated, 1921-1979 ) contains alphabetically arranged correspondence, reports and notes collected by Ralph Pancallo.
Series II: Agreements ( undated, 1922-1980 ), contains alphabetically arranged contracts (including Scale of Wages and Working Conditions and Conditions of Employment Agreements) between employers and the Manchester Typographical Union, New Britain Typographical Union No. 679 and Waterville Typographical Union.
Series III: Printed Material ( undated, 1952-1979 ) includes publications of the American Newspaper Guild, the International Typographical Union and the New England Conference of Typographical Unions. The records have been arranged alphabetically by creating body.
Series IV: International Typographical Union: Constitutions and By-Laws ( 1958-1976 ) contains a complete set of constitutions together with by-law changes.
Series V: International Typographical Union: 107th Convention Film ( 1966 ) contains two reels of film from the annual convention.
Series VI: 1994 Addendeum ( undated, 1911-1953 ) consists of additional materials Mr. Pancallo donated to the Archives ☀ Special Collections in 1994. The series is comprised of union meeting minutes, financial ledgers, and printed materials of the New Britain Typographical Union, No. 679 spanning the years 1911 - 1958. Of particular interest, the series includes correspondence, clippings and printed materials pertaining to contract negotiations of 1946-47, when Pancallo served as chairman of the Scales Committee in the union.
Series VII: 1996 Addendum ( undated, 1882-1984 ) consists of printed materials Mr. Pancallo donated to the Archives ☀ Special Collections in 1996. The bulk of the addendum consists of convention reports from the International Typographical Union and the New England Conference of Typographical Unions. Other materials include publications from a variety of local typographical unions as well as the AFL-CIO. The records have been arranged alphabetically by creating body.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining Connecticut labor. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Central Maine morning sentinel (Watervilee, Me.: Newspaper); Press—Employees—Labor unions—United States.; Printing industry—Employees—Labor unions—Connecticut.; Printing industry—Employees—Labor unions—New England.; Labor unions—Periodicals.; American newspapers—Maine.; Labor laws and legislation—United States.; Collective labor agreements—Printing industry—Maine.; Collective labor agreements—Printing industry—Connecticut.; Italian-Americans—Connecticut.; Connecticut—Population elements—Italians.; New Britain (Conn.)—Population elements—Italians.; Connecticut—Business, industries, and trades—Printing.; New Britain (Conn.)—Business, industries, and trades—Printing.; New Hampshire—Business, industries, and trades—Printing.; Maine—Business, industries, and trades—Printing.; Connecticut—Labor—Trade-unions.; New Britain (Conn.)—Labor—Trade-unions.; New Hampshire—Labor—Trade-unions.; Manchester (N.H.)—Labor—Trade-unions.; Maine—Labor—Trade-unions.; Maine—Newspapers, periodicals, and journalism.; New Britain (Conn.)—City planning.; Connecticut—Civic and community affairs.; New Britain (Conn.)—Civic and community affairs.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Photocopies.; Notes.; Motion picture film.; Bylaws.
Occupations:
Union leader.
Restrictions on Access
These materials are not restricted.
Custodial History
The Ralph J. Pancallo Papers were donated to the University of Connecticut Foundation, for deposit in Historical Manuscripts and Archives, in February 1984.
Acquisition Information
The Ralph J. Pancallo Papers were transferred to Historical Manuscripts and Archives (now Archives & Special Collections) in 1984. In 1994 and 1996 Pancallo donated additional materials which make up the eighth and ninth series of this collection.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Subject Files, undated, 1921-1981
  - Air Traffic Controller Strike, 1981 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Citizens Job Protection Bill
    - Correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Photograph and signed act, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Printed material, 1960-1967 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Connecticut State Labor Council: Correspondence, undated, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Daddario, Emilio Q.: Correspondence (labor legislation), 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Denver Photo Engravers Union, No. 18: NLRB case, 1965 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Labor Vote Correspondence, undated, 1956 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - New Britain Labor Council, AFL-CIO
    - Constitution and By-Laws, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - New Britain League for Better Citizenship: Constitution and By-Laws, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - New Britain Police Rotation Plan: Correspondence and printed material, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - New Britain City Plan Commission: Correspondence and redevelopment report, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - New Britain Typographical Union, No. 697
    - Bond and Financial Papers, 1932-1950 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Constitution and By-Laws: revised and updated, 1965 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Honorable withdraw card, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Information letter, undated (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - New Haven Typographical Union, No. 47: Arbitration cases, undated, 1975-1979 (Box 1:, Folder 18-22)
- Series II: Agreements, undated, 1922-1980
  - Central Connecticut Typographical Union, No. 679, 1979-1980 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
  - Manchester Typographical Union, No. 679
    - Conditions of Employment, 1948 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
    - The Art Press, 1942-1947 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
    - Burnett Press, Inc., 1937 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
    - Commercial Printing Co., 1944-1947 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
    - Doulan, Thomas D., 1937 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
    - Herald Publishing Co., 1940-1980 (Box 2:, Folder 29-31)
    - Hildreth Press, 1955-1957 (Box 2:, Folder 32)
    - Lincoln Printing Co., 1936-1947 (Box 2:, Folder 33)
    - New Britain, City of: Publishers and Employing, undated (Box 2:, Folder 34)
    - Printers-Scales of Wages and Working Agreements, 1922-1924 (Box 2:, Folder 35-36)
    - Scales of Wages and Working Conditions, 1926-1938 (Box 2:, Folder 37-38)
  - Waterville Typographical Union and Guy Gannet Publishing Co., (Central Maine Morning Sentinel), 1976-1979 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
- Series III: Printed Material, undated, 1952-1979
  - American Newspaper Guild, AFL-CIO: The Guild Reporter, 1964 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
  - International Typographical Union
    - General, undated (Box 2:, Folder 41)
    - Annual Convention proceedings, 1959-1973 (Box 2:, Folder 42-44)
    - “Basic Guide on Grievance Procedures”, undated (Box 2:, Folder 45)
    - “Federal Responsibility for a Free and Competitive Press”, 1963 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
    - International Progressive Party, International, undated (Box 2:, Folder 47)
    - Progressive Campaign Committee: Constitution and By-Laws, 1979 (Box 2:, Folder 48)
    - “New Age of Printing”, [1975?] (Box 2:, Folder 49)
    - “100 Years Plus of Democratic Trade Unionism: The Story of the International Typographical Union”, [ca. 1952?] (Box 2:, Folder 50)
    - “A Study of the History of the International Typographical Union: 1852-1963.” V. 1, 1964 (Box 2:, Folder 51)
  - New England Conference of Typographical Unions: Annual Convention Proceedings, 1959-1967 (Box 2:, Folder 52)
  - Newspaper Guild, AFL-CIO: “Anatomy of a Strike,” Fall River Herald News, 1972 (Box 2:, Folder 53)
- Series IV: International Typographical Union: Constitutions and By-Laws, 1958-1976
  - Constitutions and By-Laws, 1958-1976 (Box 4:, Folder 54-63)
  - Changes in the By-Laws, 1961-1974 (Box 4:, Folder 64)
- Series V: International Typographical Union: 107th Convention Film, 1966
  - Convention Film, 1966; (2 reels) (Box 5-6)
- Series VI: 1994 Addendum, undated, 1911-1953
  - I.T.U.: “American Needs Labor Unions”, undated (Box 7:, Folder 65)
  - New Britain Typographical Union
    - Daily Benefits list, 1950 (Box 7:, Folder 66)
    - Daily cash ledger, 1950-1953 (Box 7:, Folder 67)
    - Membership dues register, 1931-1938 (Box 7:, Folder 68-69)
    - minutes of meetings, 1911-1916 (Box 7:, Folder 70)
    - Original membership register, undated (Box 7:, Folder 71)
    - Union committees and member lists, undated (Box 7:, Folder 72)
  - Binder: materials pertaining to contract negotiations, 1946-1947 (Box 8:, Folder 73)
- Series VII: 1996 Addendum, undated, 1882-1984
  - AFL-CIO: “American Federalist”, 1959 (Box 9:, Folder 74)
    - “Education: News and Views”, undated (Box 9:, Folder 75)
    - Song Book, undated (Box 9:, Folder 76)
  - Brown, Elmer (President, I.T.U.): “American Needs Unions”, undated (Box 9:, Folder 77)
    - “Unite for the Future”, c. 1961 (Box 9:, Folder 78)
  - Connecticut Federation of Labor: “Connecticut Federalist”, 1956 (Box 9:, Folder 79)
  - Connecticut State Labor Council: First Official Yearbook, 1957 (Box 9:, Folder 80)
  - I.T.U.: Convention Programs [with gaps], 1950-1972 (Box 9:, Folder 81-90)
    - Convention Programs [with gaps], 1974-1983 (Box 10:, Folder 91-98)
    - Book of Laws of the I.T.U., 1882 (Box 10:, Folder 99)
    - “Rats for Hire: The Story of Professional Strikebreakers”, undated (Box 10:, Folder 100)
  - New Britain Typographical Union, No. 679: Agreement, 1966 (Box 10:, Folder 101)
  - New England Conference of Typographical Unions: Convention Programs [with gaps], 1962-1968 (Box 10:, Folder 102-105)
  - New Haven Typographical Union, No. 47: 100th Anniversary, 1960 (Box 10:, Folder 106)
  - New York Typographical Union, No. 6 Bulletin, 1984 (Box 10:, Folder 107)
  - The Reporter, 1960 (Box 10:, Folder 108)
  - Schneider, Clifford L.: “Printshop Profiles”, undated (Box 10:, Folder 109)